Elmer Holmes Davis Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Elmer Holmes Davis Papers 1865-1957 1946-1955
MSS17889
Davis, Elmer Holmes, 1890-1958
7,800 items
25 containers
10 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Author, journalist, news analyst, and government official. Correspondence, manuscripts of articles and early pieces of fiction, subject file, radio scripts, biographical material, lectures and speeches, and photographs relating to Davis's career.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Davis, Elmer Holmes, 1890-1958.; Davis, Elmer Holmes, 1890-1958. But We Were Born Free. 1954.; De Voto, Bernard, 1897-1955--Correspondence.; Murrow, Edward R.--Correspondence.; Ross, Harold Wallace, 1892-1951--Correspondence.; Thurber, James, 1894-1961--Correspondence.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972--Correspondence.; Van Loon, Hendrik Willem, 1882-1944--Correspondence.; Welles, Sumner, 1892-1961--Correspondence.; White, William Allen, 1868-1944--Correspondence.; Wilson, Carolyn A., -1960--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Broadcasting Company.; Columbia Broadcasting System, inc.; United States. Office of War Information.
Subjects
Journalism.; Literature, Modern--20th century.; World politics.; World War, 1914-1918--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.
Places
United States--Politics and government--20th century.
Occupations
Authors.; Journalists.; News analysts.; Public officials.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Elmer Holmes Davis, author, journalist, news analyst, and government official, were given to the Library of Congress by Davis and his widow, Florence MacMillan Davis, in 1954 and 1959. A letter was given by William R. Allen in 1962 and a radio script by Reid and Nancy Campbell Joyner in 2011.
Additional Guides
A note on the Elmer Holmes Davis Papers appeared in the Library's Information Bulletin 18, no. 20 (May 18, 1959): 269-70. A brief description of the papers also appeared in the Library's Quarterly Journal of Current Acquisitions 17, no. 3 (May 1960): 185.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Elmer Holmes Davis are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1890, Jan. 13 Born, Aurora, Ind.
1910 1911 A.B. and A.M., Franklin College, Franklin, Ind.
1912 1914 Rhodes Scholar, Queen's College, Oxford University, Oxford, England
1914 1924 Worked on staff of New York Times
1917 Married Florence MacMillan
1920 1935 Created and wrote for the character Godfrey G. Gloom, who was a columnist and political commentator
1939 1942 News analyst, Columbia Broadcasting Co.
1942 1945 Director, Office of War Information
1945 1954 Free-lance writer, radio commentator, and lecturer
1954 Published But We Were Born Free. Garden City, New York: Garden City Books
1955 Published Two Minutes Till Midnight, a sequel to But We Were Born Free. Indianapolis, Indiana: Bobbs-Merrill
1958, May 18 Died, Washington, D. C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Elmer Holmes Davis (1890-1958) span the years 1865-1957, with the bulk of the material dating from 1946 to 1955. The papers are organized into the following series: General Correspondence, Personal and Literary File, Subject File, Radio Scripts, and Addition.
The General Correspondence contains mostly letters relating to Davis's career. He kept little of his personal incoming and outgoing letters. Davis did, however, retain some early correspondence written by his parents, his wife, and a few others. Notable are the 1917 letters from Carolyn A. Wilson who reported from France during World War I for the Chicago Tribune and corresponded with Davis about what she observed. Later correspondence reflects Davis's involvement in the political and literary fields. Correspondents include Bernard Augustine De Voto, Edward R. Murrow, Harold Wallace Ross, James Thurber, Harry S. Truman, Hendrik Willem van Loon, Sumner Welles, and William Allen White.
The Personal and Literary File contains biographical material, lectures and speeches, photographs, and printed copies of many of Davis's articles and early pieces of fiction as well as the typescript of But We Were Born Free. Of interest are photographs taken during a visit to Pearl Harbor, Hawaii, in 1944, and currency produced by the First National Bank of Aurora, Indiana, in 1865, where Davis's father worked.
The Subject File, devoted mainly to world events, contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, magazine articles, government publications, notes, and press releases issued by news bureaus and government agencies. Of interest are the files on the Office of War Information that include a report to the president for the years 1942-1945 and items relating to Davis's service as director including his file card from the Nazi Propaganda Ministry, memoranda of conversations with government officials, and correspondence and clippings relating to the dispute between the Office of War Information and its overseas branch. Further correspondence relating to the Office of War Information is in the General Correspondence.
Radio Scripts contains Davis's original scripts of broadcasts for the Columbia Broadcasting System and the American Broadcasting Company. For 1946, there is also a set of approved scripts. The Addition is comprised of a radio script dated 16 February 1942.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
General Correspondence, 1893-1957
Personal and Literary File, 1865-1955
Subject File, circa 1941-circa 1955
Radio Scripts, 1942-1955
Addition, 1942
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1893-1957 (Box 1-3)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1893, 1906-1946, (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1947-1949, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1950-1957, undated, (6 folders) (Box 3)
- Personal and Literary File, 1865-1955 (Box 4-5)
  Biographical and family material, clippings, speeches and lectures, memorabilia, photographs, articles, typescript of his book But We Were Born Free, booklets, a novel, and short stories.
  Arranged under personal or literary and therein by type of material.
  - Personal (Box 4)
    - Biographical and family material (Box 4)
      - Clippings, 1903, 1911-1912, 1941-1953 (Box 4)
      - Currency and documents relating to Elam Holmes Davis (father), 1865, 1873, 1888, 1896, 1912-1913 (Box 4)
      - Memorabilia, 1910, 1920-1921, 1934-1950, undated (Box 4)
      - Photographs, 1944, undated (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, 1925, 1934-1935, 1941-1954 (Box 4)
    - Printed matter, 1943-1953, undated (Box 4)
    - Speeches and lectures, 1940, 1946-1953, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Transcripts from the British Broadcasting Company and the Columbia Broadcasting System, 1948-1949 (Box 4)
  - Literary (Box 4)
    - Articles and book reviews (Box 4)
      - 1915-1929, (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - 1930-1955, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Book, But We Were Born Free, typescript, 1954 (Box 5)
    - Booklets, 1920, 1942 (Box 5)
    - Novel, "He Drives Furiously," undated (Box 5)
    - Short stories, 1921-1938, (4 folders) (Box 5)
- Subject File, circa 1941-circa 1955 (Box 6-12)
  Correspondence, clippings, congressional reports, notes, press releases, printed matter, research papers, and other material.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Africa-Brownell, Herbert, (14 folders) (Box 6)
  - Campaign information-Democratic party policies, (10 folders) (Box 7)
  - Education-Foreign policy, (6 folders) (Box 8)
  - France-Italy, (18 folders) (Box 9)
  - Japan-Office of War Information, (10 folders) (Box 10)
  - Oil-Republican party policies, (16 folders) (Box 11)
  - Soviet Union-Yugoslavia, (13 folders) (Box 12)
- Radio Scripts, 1942-1955 (Box 13-25)
  Original radio scripts.
  - Mar. 1942, Aug. 1944 (Box 13)
  - Dec. 1945 (Box 13)
  - 1946 (Box 13)
    - Original (Box 13)
      - Jan.-Oct., (4 folders) (Box 13)
      - Nov.-Dec., (1 folder) (Box 14)
    - Approved, (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1947 (Box 14)
    - Jan.-Mar., (5 folders) (Box 14)
    - Apr.-July, (11 folders) (Box 15)
    - Aug.-Dec., (5 folders) (Box 16)
  - 1948 (Box 16)
    - Jan.-Mar., (3 folders) (Box 16)
    - Apr-Dec., (9 folders) (Box 17)
  - 1949 (Box 18)
    - Jan.-July, (7 folders) (Box 18)
    - Aug.-Dec., (5 folders) (Box 19)
  - 1950 (Box 19)
    - Jan.-Mar., (3 folders) (Box 19)
    - Apr.-Dec., (9 folders) (Box 20)
  - 1951 (Box 21)
    - Jan.-June, (6 folders) (Box 21)
    - July-Dec., (6 folders) (Box 22)
  - 1952 (Box 22)
    - Jan.-Feb. (Box 22)
    - Mar.-Oct., (4 folders) (Box 23)
    - Nov.-Dec. (Box 24)
  - 1953 (Box 24)
    - Jan.-May, (5 folders) (Box 24)
    - June-Oct., (5 folders) (Box 25)
  - 1954 (Box 25)
  - 1955 (Box 25)
- Addition, 1942 (Box 25)
  Radio script.
  - Radio script, 1942, Feb. 16 (Box 25)